<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-10T12:48:58-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jekyll-Blog-Undiscovered</title><subtitle>Final build of the Jekyll blog that will be featured in Maxx-Undiscovered Tutorial</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Three Coaching Spots With Leo Now Open</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/27/Coaching/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Three Coaching Spots With Leo Now Open" /><published>2019-05-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/27/Coaching</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/27/Coaching/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Stop acting so small. You are the universe in ecstatic motion.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;― Rumi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friends,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m opening up two spots for my 1-on-1 coaching service, which is aimed for those who would like to start changing their lives, shifting their patterns, and starting true transformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m looking for people who:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are doing meaningful work:&lt;/strong&gt; You’re creating, you’re starting a non-profit, you’re volunteering, you’re changing lives, you’re serving a team or community, you care about the people you’re serving.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are being held back by their patterns in uncertainty&lt;/strong&gt;: Your meaningful work is filled with uncertainty, which brings up habitual patterns … maybe you put things off, you try to control everything, you feel overwhelmed, you feel anxiety, you shrink away from public speaking or putting your work in public, you take on too much, you play a smaller game than you should, you feel resentment, you run to comfort and distraction, you don’t delegate. Maybe not all of these, but possibly a few of them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are ready to take action and commit to training:&lt;/strong&gt; I’m not looking for someone who will sign up and then not actually do the training. Maybe you’ve put things off before, but if you sign up with me, I want a commitment that you’re going to make the time to do the training, show up fully for the calls and your practices, and be all in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are not afraid of mindfulness practices and are willing to go deeper:&lt;/strong&gt; You’ve meditated for a little bit now, and don’t mind going deep into mindfulness practices, being vulnerable, being radically honest, and opening up to new training.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are ready to commit some time, effort and money into something meaningful: What is so important to you that you’re ready to commit a significant amount of time, effort and money to it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is that you? What is meaningful to you? Who do you care deeply about? What change do you want to create in the world?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-the-training-works&quot;&gt;How the Training Works&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll start with a free call, to get to know each other, and see if it’s the right fit. You won’t be under any obligation after the call. Then I’ll send you a proposal, and if you sign on, we’ll commit to training together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we’ll meet twice a month, on video call, and dive into your patterns, what’s holding you back, what you want to create, and how you can train to shift those patterns. We’ll work flexibly, but with commitment and accountability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll give you practices/assignments to do between calls — this is where the real change takes place. You’ll log your training, and I’ll give you feedback on your log so that you can adjust the training if needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we’ll see what magic happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ready to train with me?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apply here today for one of the two spots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;client-testimonial&quot;&gt;Client Testimonial&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a testimonial from one of my recent clients:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I had the usual goals to start with (more mindfulness, more discipline, less procrastination – you name it) which I have been aiming at – and missing – for a long time. Leo’s kind and extremely open approach made me feel safe and capable of sharing honestly my wins and failures. During our work together, Leo helped me to flank the obstacles that was resisting my futile head-on attacks. Due to the coaching experience, I am more capable of picking the right battles, distinguishing the important from irrelevant and accepting discomfort as a natural part of the journey.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;strong&gt;Ales Balcar, trainer for Amazon.com&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Helton</name></author><category term="standups" /><summary type="html">“Stop acting so small. You are the universe in ecstatic motion.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Mindful Method for When You’re Tired</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/23/Tired/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Mindful Method for When You’re Tired" /><published>2019-05-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/23/Tired</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/23/Tired/">&lt;p&gt;My family &amp;amp; I flew back to California after nine months of being in Guam, and boy are our arms tired! OK, our entire bodies are tired, and our brains — we’re suffering from jet lag and feeling tired during the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t necessarily a problem — jet lag is to be expected, after all — but tiredness can affect everything in your life. I find myself less able to do work, more overwhelmed when I’m behind on email and messages, less able to keep up with healthy habits, more likely to eat junk food, and in worse moods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being tired can have such huge effects on us. And many people are tired much of the time, from being overworked and underslept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what can we do? Well, there are the usual methods of trying to get better sleep, like better sleep hygiene, setting a consistent bedtime and wake time, and so forth. These are highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what do you do today, when you’re still tired? What can you do tomorrow if you’re tired then too?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s how I try to practice in the middle of the tiredness, which is sometimes unavoidable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recognize that my battery is low.&lt;/strong&gt; First I notice that I’m feeling tired, that my capacity to do things is lower than normal, that I am not as sharp or in as good a mood as I normally am (I’m normally a super dynamo, you know!). Bring awareness to my state.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lower my expectations.&lt;/strong&gt; Next, I bring acceptance to the fact that I’m just not going to be super productive or on top of things as much as I’d like. I recognize and accept that I just want to curl up in a ball, watch TV and eat junk food. With this acceptance of my lowered capacity, I try not to expect myself to get too much done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experience the tiredness.&lt;/strong&gt; We try to eat junk food and procrastinate in order to not feel the tiredness. Instead, I try to actually feel it. That means to fully experience the tiredness, as if it’s just as delicious as any other experience. I try to bring curiosity to the experience — what is it like? How do my eyes feel behind my droopy eyelids? What does my face feel like? What about my chest? Throat? Gut? Legs? I try to feel it as an experience, not something I need to get rid of.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Give myself compassion.&lt;/strong&gt; This might be so obvious or trite that many readers will skip this step, but I recommend that you give this a genuine shot. I pause and give myself some love — I’m feeling tired and down, so I wish for my suffering to end. It’s the same feeling if someone you loved were feeling anxious or hurt — how would you send them love? Do the same exact thing for yourself. This is a physical feeling of sending love to your tiredness, not an intellectual concept. Practice it now!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim for small victories.&lt;/strong&gt; As I have a lowered capacity, I just try to get small victories when I can. Don’t have energy in the morning? Maybe I can just answer a couple of emails. Don’t have the capacity to write a blog post? Maybe I can just write two paragraphs. So I’m not entirely abdicating my responsibilities when I’m tired — I’m just trying to do a small amount. It makes a huge difference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If I give in to temptation, really be present with it.&lt;/strong&gt; If I decide to go for the pizza or ice cream, that’s nothing to feel guilty about. But for goodness sake, don’t do it mindlessly! If I’m going to eat ice cream, I want to be entirely present with the sensation of the sweetness on my tongue, the coldness in my mouth, going down my throat. Savor it. Experience it entirely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s my mindful method, and I am imperfect at it. I violate every single one of these. But I try to practice, and when I do, it’s always wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Helton</name></author><category term="standups" /><summary type="html">My family &amp;amp; I flew back to California after nine months of being in Guam, and boy are our arms tired! OK, our entire bodies are tired, and our brains — we’re suffering from jet lag and feeling tired during the day.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Riding the Turbulence of Life Like a Wave</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/21/Turbulence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Riding the Turbulence of Life Like a Wave" /><published>2019-05-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/21/Turbulence</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/21/Turbulence/">&lt;p&gt;We’re in the middle of a big move back to California from Guam, and things are in great flux. Saying goodby to everyone, packing and shipping stuff, not having a home yet, traveling with kids on a couple long flights, moving our old stuff from storage in a U-Haul, finding our way in a new city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is turbulent right now — though if we think about it, it almost always is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not a surfer, but I imagine that I can let myself be overwhelmed and crushed by the turbulence … or I can ride it like a surfer might ride a wave. You don’t control the wave or know how it will turn out, you just have to navigate it moment to moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we can learn to ride the rolling uncertainty of our lives like a wave, staying open each moment to what unfolds, we can live without as much stress and anxiety, and just be present to what is happening. Maybe even enjoy ourselves in the middle of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what would that be like?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, it seems to be staying present with the feelings of uncertainty that come up for me, instead of trying to ignore them or get away from them. That means allowing myself to feel the turbulence, not constantly staying distracted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to be trying to be curious about what is unfolding, about what this particular moment is like, without needing to know what comes next exactly. Without needing it to be any certain way. And if I do expect it to be a certain way, being present with my feelings of frustration or stress when it doesn’t turn out to be that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to be about surrendering, a bit, as I relax my constant need for control. I don’t have all the information I need to perfectly plan out my life — there’s so much uncertainty about everything, that I can’t possibly know how things should go, what I should do exactly, what will come next. So should I try to plan for every possible outcome, be incredibly prepared for any possible scenario, when I can’t know what might happen? Or can I relax and surrender, trusting that I can deal with whatever does come up. So far, that’s always been true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to be about dealing with what’s right in front of me, in the moment. I can’t deal with every possible scenario that might come in the future, but I can be fully open to what’s happening right now. I can be as present as I can with this situation, and figure out what needs to be done right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also seems to be about learning to love this moment, as it unfolds, as it is. I don’t know what will come next, but what’s happening now is completely new, a beautiful surprise. Instead of worrying so much about what is still to come, I can open my eyes to what’s right here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then fall in love with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walking into the unknown can be scary … but at the same time, it can also be a time of discovering love for a fresh experience. It can be a time of walking into pure joy at the miracle of life that’s just emerging in this moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is breathtaking and lovely.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Helton</name></author><category term="standups" /><summary type="html">We’re in the middle of a big move back to California from Guam, and things are in great flux. Saying goodby to everyone, packing and shipping stuff, not having a home yet, traveling with kids on a couple long flights, moving our old stuff from storage in a U-Haul, finding our way in a new city.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buying Too Much Stuff is Driven By Uncertainty</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/15/Buying/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buying Too Much Stuff is Driven By Uncertainty" /><published>2019-05-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/15/Buying</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/15/Buying/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you are invested in security and certainty, you are on the wrong planet.” &lt;strong&gt;~Pema Chodron&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eva and I and our two younger kids are in the process of moving back to California from Guam, where we've been living with family for the last 9 months. As we pack our stuff, get some stuff ready to ship to California, and donate other things to charity … it is a great time to reflect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do people have so much stuff?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though we have relatively little compared to most, we've still managed to accumulate too much, from getting gifts from other people to buying necessities (and non-necessities) along the way. Stuff just piles up over time — that's the nature of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But most of it is not necessary. &lt;strong&gt;Most of our stuff, we buy because of one feeling: the feeling of uncertainty.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the underlying groundlessness, shakiness, insecurity we feel about the future and the present moment. It's the uncertainty we feel all day long, every day, to varying degrees. It's what causes us to feel fear, stress, anxiety, worry, even anger. It's what causes us to procrastinate and put off our healthy and productive habits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The feeling of uncertainty is the root of our buying too much stuff.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about these examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are going on a trip, and you’re feeling a bit nervous about it, so you do research and buy a bunch of stuff to take with you to help you feel more secure, prepared, certain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You’re going to attend a conference, and it brings up some anxiety, so you get some gear to help you feel more prepared.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You get into a new hobby, and don’t know what you’re doing so feel a lot of uncertainty, and do a ton of research for days, buying everything you can possibly think of to be fully prepared.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are hosting a social gathering and this is giving you some stress, so you buy a bunch of things to make sure the party goes as well as you can hope for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are feeling a lot of disruption and uncertainty in your life, and find yourself procrastinating on things while doing a lot of online shopping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are feeling uncertainty about yourself, about your looks. To help with that, you buy a lot of nice clothes and gear to make you feel better about yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could go on with endless examples, but you get the idea. Uncertainty brings with it an urge to get certainty, control, preparedness, security. And so we buy stuff to try to get that feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-futility-of-shopping-to-deal-with-uncertainty&quot;&gt;The Futility of Shopping to Deal with Uncertainty&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don't like the feeling of uncertainty and insecurity – we try to get rid of it as soon as we can, get away from it, push it away. We have lots of habitual patterns we've built up over the years to deal with this uncertainty and insecurity … and buying things is one of the most common, other than procrastination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the thing: it doesn't actually give us any certainty or security. We buy things and we're not really more prepared, in control, or secure. We hope we will be, and yet the feelings of uncertainty and insecurity are still there. So we have to buy some more stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're looking for the magical answer to give us control and security, but it doesn’t exist. Life is uncertain. Always. It's the defining feature of life. Read the quote from Pema Chodron at the top — it says it all, we have to accept the uncertainty of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in fact, this is the answer to our drive to buy too much stuff — if we lean into the uncertainty, embrace it, learn to become comfortable with it, we can stop buying so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can learn to live with little, sitting with the uncertainty of it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-practice-of-opening-to-uncertainty-to-live-with-little&quot;&gt;The Practice of Opening to Uncertainty, to Live with Little&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine owning very little, living in a spare room, eating simple whole food, not being involved in social media, just working, reading, walking, spending time with loved ones. Meditating, drinking tea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a life of very little, and is beautiful in its simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then uncertainty comes up, as it inevitably does. You have a trip, you have to go to a party, you have a new kind of project to take on, you are starting a new venture. You’re feeling insecurity and uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s how to practice with it instead of buying something:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice you have the urge to buy something (or procrastinate, get control of everything, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice that underlying the urge is a feeling of uncertainty, that you don’t want.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instead of rushing to follow your urge to buy something, pause and just sit with the uncertainty for a minute or two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turn your attention to the physical feeling of uncertainty in your body. Where is it located? What does it feel like?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stay with the feeling and get really curious about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relax around the feeling. Be generous with it, giving it compassion, openness, gratitude, love.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice that this is just a sensation, just an experience, nothing you need to run from, hate, or push away. You can be with it, even open up to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this practice, you don’t need to fill your life with more stuff. This is my practice right now, as I see the effects of too much stuff that’s come into my family’s life. Sit with the uncertainty, embrace it, and fall in love with the groundlessness of my life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Helton</name></author><category term="standups" /><summary type="html">“If you are invested in security and certainty, you are on the wrong planet.” ~Pema Chodron</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The 11 Life Lessons It Turns Out I’ve Taught My Six Kids</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/09/Lessons/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 11 Life Lessons It Turns Out I’ve Taught My Six Kids" /><published>2019-05-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/09/Lessons</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/09/Lessons/">&lt;p&gt;On my 46th birthday recently, my (mostly adult) kids wrote out a list of lessons I’d taught each of them in their lives so far. Each wrote their own list, and my wife Eva sweetly put them together in a notebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I read through them, I felt like crying. It’s so incredibly touching that they appreciate what I’ve been trying to pass on to them, things I’ve been learning and want them to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a father, there are few things more meaningful than to see how you’ve helped your kids through your example and talks over the years. We have a mixed family of 6 kids, aging from 13 years old to 26 years, and all of them are wonderful human beings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out, there were some lessons that all or most of the kids put on their list, which I’m going to share with you here. These lessons they had in common made me wonder if these were the more powerful lessons, or if they were simply the ones I talked about the most. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here they are, roughly ordered in how frequently they showed up on my kids’ lists:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t be afraid to make mistakes, and it’s okay to fail.&lt;/strong&gt; This was tied (with the next one) as the most common lesson on their lists — it made all their lists, I think. I really love that this lesson hit home with them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have empathy &amp;amp; try to see things from others’ perspectives.&lt;/strong&gt; This was the other lesson on all their lists, and again, it’s beautiful that they all took this to heart. I’ve tried to show them this through my actions, though of course I’m not at all perfect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Push out of your comfort zone.&lt;/strong&gt; This is another one I’ve tried to teach by example, from running several marathons and an ultramarathon to doing things that scare me, like speaking on stage or writing books. This lesson is so important to me that&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t spend more than you have.&lt;/strong&gt; This is such a simple idea, but one that is rarely followed. I’m glad my kids are starting out with this mindset — live within your means, save as much as you can.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appreciate what you have &amp;amp; enjoy where you are right now.&lt;/strong&gt; I love this one. It’s something that I try to embody, but also remind them when they are thinking about what they don’t have. Each time we’re stuck in complaint, it’s an opportunity to wake up to the beauty that’s in front of us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sadness is a part of life, and there’s nothing wrong with feeling it.&lt;/strong&gt; Despite what I said in the previous item, it’s OK to feel sadness, pain, grief, frustration, anxiety, anger. In fact, most of us never want to feel those things, so we’ll do whatever we can to ignore them or get away from the feelings. Instead, I try to actually feel those things, as an experience. It teaches me about struggle — if we’re not willing to face our own struggles, how can we be there for others when they struggle?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t give up just because something gets hard.&lt;/strong&gt; As new adults, our four oldest kids are facing various struggles in new ways. This is part of growth, of course, but struggles never feel good. My job as dad has been to encourage them not to give up just because it’s hard — to keep going, and to use the struggle to grow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But don’t overwork yourself.&lt;/strong&gt; That said, I’m not a fan of overwork. I believe the brain doesn’t function well if you keep studying or working past the point of exhaustion, so I try to teach them about taking breaks, resting, going outside and moving.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s okay to be weird in public. Have fun.&lt;/strong&gt; I’m not sure why several of them had this on the list — they must have learned to be weird from someone else? OK, in truth, they might have gotten it from my tendency to dance and skip with them while we’re out walking around in a city, or to encourage us all to do weird things as a group, no matter what other people might think.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your reality is a reflection of the narrative you tell yourself.&lt;/strong&gt; This is something I learned late in life, and I’m glad my kids are learning this. The good news is that you can learn to drop that narrative, if it leads to suffering. What would this moment be like without a narrative? Beautiful and free.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make people laugh. It makes their day brighter.&lt;/strong&gt; I’m so happy they picked up this important lesson from me! With my kids, I’m mostly always joking, except for when I get (too) serious about teaching them an important lesson. The rest of the time, I try to take a lighthearted approach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love my kids with all my heart, and it has been a privilege to be their dad. I take 10% of the credit and give the rest to their moms, grandparents, and themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lovescrewed.com/leo-lessons/&quot; title=&quot;Btw, you can read Chloe’s full list in her blog post&quot;&gt;Btw, you can read Chloe’s full list in her blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also … from them, I’ve learned some lessons that are just as important:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kids deserve to be heard, to be listened to, to be respected.&lt;/strong&gt; I started out as a dad with the idea that what I say goes, and they just need to listen to me! But over the years, I’ve learned to listen to them, and treat them as I’d want to be treated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kids have tender hearts that hurt when you aren’t kind to them.&lt;/strong&gt; As a young dad, my frustrations and insecurities led me to angry bursts of scolding, yelling, spanking. I’ve grown since then, but more importantly, I’ve learned to see the tenderness of their hearts, and how it hurts to be yelled at by someone they trust and love so much. I am much more gentle with those hearts these days.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I should relax and not take myself so seriously.&lt;/strong&gt; Whenever I think too much of myself, my kids humble me. Whenever I get too serious, my kids laugh at me. I love that playful reminder to loosen up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dads are goofy, dorky, uncool. And that’s how we should be.&lt;/strong&gt; I sometimes harbor the notion that I can be a “cool” dad. When I try to break out newish slang or reference a meme, my kids will tease me about it. When I break out a joke or pun that I think is hilarious, they’ll laugh while rolling their eyes and calling it a “dad joke.” So I’ve learned just to embrace my uncoolness, and be myself with them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All they need is love.&lt;/strong&gt; There are lots of things to stress out about as parents, and nowadays we tend to obsess about getting everything right with our kids. But really, we’re stressing about it too much. All the details are just details — there’s only one thing that really matters. They want you to love them. And to receive their love. That’s all. Feed them, clothe them, shelter them, educate them, sure … but beyond that, they just want you to love them. Drop everything that gets in the way of that and let it come out as simply and clearly as you can.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you, my loves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Helton</name></author><category term="standups" /><summary type="html">On my 46th birthday recently, my (mostly adult) kids wrote out a list of lessons I’d taught each of them in their lives so far. Each wrote their own list, and my wife Eva sweetly put them together in a notebook.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Focus: Training to Open in the Middle of Shakiness</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/06/Deep-Focus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Focus: Training to Open in the Middle of Shakiness" /><published>2019-05-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/06/Deep-Focus</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/06/Deep-Focus/">&lt;p&gt;When we set out to work on a meaningful, important task, something interesting happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We feel quite a bit shaky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s the feeling you get when you step into uncertain ground, where you don’t know exactly what you’re doing or whether you can do it, where you feel a bit lost or don’t have solid ground under your feet. This is the shakiness of groundlessness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing wrong with feeling shaky and groundless, but our minds don’t really like it. In fact, we’ve trained our minds to run from this uncertainty and shakiness, to go to distraction, procrastination, busywork, trying to get control, or going to a host of other habitual patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We feel the shakiness and immediately do whatever we can to avoid feeling it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we could just feel the shakiness and not need to run? What if we could practice mindfulness in the middle of it, and stay in the groundlessness? We might even learn to be completely happy in the shakiness, to see it as the place we want to be if we want to do anything meaningful, if we want to have an impact on the world and make a difference in the lives of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can do this by training ourselves in Deep Focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-shift-into-deep-focus&quot;&gt;The Shift into Deep Focus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deep Focus is simply staying focused on one task for longer than we normally might, staying in the middle of the task despite urges to switch to something else, despite our habitual patterns. It’s immersing yourself into the task, creating undistracted space where you can stay in the shakiness and give it your entire being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How often do we actually give ourselves entirely to a task? What would it be like to shift into this mode more often?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do it, you have to clear everything away and set an intention to dive deep into the task. You have to pick an important task that is meaningful to you, that is worth this kind of diving in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll also want to create some kind of structure to hold you in this focus when things get shaky and you want to run. The structure might be some kind of accountability, some kind of structured session that is timed, has no other options, and no wifi … you can find the structure that works for you over time if you experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is a very different way of relating to a task. Instead of it being something you need to rush through to get to the next task, it becomes worthy of your full attention, a destination worthy of staying in, an activity worthy of your full devotion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of it being a place of shakiness you need to run from, it becomes a place of breathtaking groundlessness, where you can savor the quality of uncertainty while also appreciating this place where you can be of service to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-training&quot;&gt;The Training&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do we train ourselves to stay in Deep Focus instead of running from the shakiness?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We commit ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We find some accountability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have daily training sessions. They don’t have to be long — in fact, I recommend just a daily session of 10 minutes for the first week. This is a proven technique that I’ve used with thousands of people, myself included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We treat these sessions as sacred ground, and devote our entire being to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to train with me and a thousand others, join my &lt;a href=&quot;http://seachange.zenhabits.net/&quot; title=&quot;Sea Change Program&quot;&gt;Sea Change Program&lt;/a&gt;, where we’re doing the Dive Into Important Tasks challenge this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you &lt;a href=&quot;https://seachange.zenhabits.net/&quot; title=&quot;join Sea Change today&quot;&gt;join Sea Change today&lt;/a&gt; (with a 7-day free trial), you can join the challenge and get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An article each week to help you dive into the challenge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A community of people supporting each other, including small teams you can join to hold you accountable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A live video webinar with me, where I give a talk and then answer your questions live&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A huge content of library to help you change the habits you’ve always wanted to change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://seachange.zenhabits.net/&quot; title=&quot;Join Sea Change today (7 days free, then $15/month)&quot;&gt;Join Sea Change today (7 days free, then $15/month).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Helton</name></author><category term="standups" /><summary type="html">When we set out to work on a meaningful, important task, something interesting happens.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Simplify Your Day to Have a Greater Impact</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/02/Impact/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Simplify Your Day to Have a Greater Impact" /><published>2019-05-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/02/Impact</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/05/02/Impact/">&lt;p&gt;Our society is obsessed with productivity and optimizing our lives — having the perfect routine, perfect diet, perfect productivity system, perfect todo app, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s an ideal that not only doesn’t exist, it’s harmful to our health and happiness. And what’s more, it’s completely misguided — what many of us really want to do with our work is do meaningful work and have an impact on the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how can we let go of the focus on productivity and optimizing, while still doing meaningful work and having an impact?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simplify. Focus on the important, meaningful tasks instead of churning. And actually dive into those meaningful tasks instead of procrastinating because of the uncertainty that comes with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Look at your task list and email/messages inbox and pick the most meaningful tasks —&lt;/strong&gt; there’s a good chance you’ve been putting them off. Instead, when you don’t go to your favorite distractions, you are likely to churn through smaller tasks, answering messages, checking on inboxes and updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is because meaningful, important tasks come with great uncertainty.&lt;/strong&gt; We habitually respond to this uncertainty by avoiding it, going to distraction and easier tasks that make us feel less uncertain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the result is that we’re churning through a lot of busywork, spending our days doing a lot but not getting a lot accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, we can simplify:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick meaningful tasks, and focus on those.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create space by clearing away distractions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Letting the busywork get pushed until later in the day, when we set aside room for those.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And putting our entire being into the meaningful, important tasks.
Imagine clearing out space in your day by simplifying, letting go of the small tasks, not constantly answering messages and emails, and instead giving yourself the generous gift of focusing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’d get the meaningful tasks done, and feel like your work is more meaningful. Those tasks would make a greater impact, and over time, you’d have a great impact on the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All because you simplified and focused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, I challenge you to join me in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenhabits.net/important-tasks/&quot; title=&quot;Dive Into the Important Tasks&quot;&gt;Dive Into the Important Tasks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://seachange.zenhabits.net/&quot; title=&quot;Join my Sea Change Program today to be a part of the challenge&quot;&gt;Join my Sea Change Program today to be a part of the challenge.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Helton</name></author><category term="standups" /><summary type="html">Our society is obsessed with productivity and optimizing our lives — having the perfect routine, perfect diet, perfect productivity system, perfect todo app, and more.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Dive Into Important Tasks Challenge</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/04/29/Important-Tasks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Dive Into Important Tasks Challenge" /><published>2019-04-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/04/29/Important-Tasks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/zen-habits/standups/2019/04/29/Important-Tasks/">&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing we can do more to further our meaningful work and make the impact that we want to make in the world than to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick our most important, meaningful tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And dive into them with full focus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, it seems to be a challenge for almost every person on this planet. Very few people regularly overcome distraction, procrastination, the urge to do small tasks or check email and messages, rationalization and running from discomfort to our usual comforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in May, I’m launching a challenge in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://seachange.zenhabits.net/&quot; title=&quot;Sea Change Program&quot;&gt;Sea Change Program&lt;/a&gt; called &lt;strong&gt;Dive Into Important Tasks&lt;/strong&gt;. It starts on Monday, May 6, but you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://seachange.zenhabits.net/&quot; title=&quot;join today&quot;&gt;join today&lt;/a&gt; and commit to the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This challenge is about picking out your high-impact, high-priority tasks every day, and then diving into it, letting go of the urge to go to distractions, the urge to procrastinate, the uncertainty that comes with these meaningful tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s about overcoming our age-old habits of procrastination, and diving into our meaningful work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s how the challenge works:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Week 1: Pick 1 meaningful task a day and do 10 minutes of it first thing in the morning&lt;/strong&gt; (or whenever you start working).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Week 2: Do 2 sessions of 10 minutes your meaningful task first thing when you start working each day.&lt;/strong&gt; Break up the two sessions with a 5-minute break. We’re training our ability to stay focused on what’s important, but in doable sessions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Week 3: Pick 2 important tasks each day, and do 3 10-minute sessions.&lt;/strong&gt; Two sessions can be for the first task, then the third for the second task. Sessions have a 5-minute break in between. Again, we’re further training ourselves to stay on task and not put it off.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Week 4: Pick 3 important tasks each day, and do 4 10-minute sessions.&lt;/strong&gt; Split up the 4 sessions however you like between the 3 important tasks. You can take a longer break between them if needed, so that you don’t have to spend a consecutive hour doing these sessions but can spread them out in the beginning part of your work day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the challenge, I’ll provide articles about the focus sessions and how to choose and dive into the important tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-benefits-of-this-training&quot;&gt;The Benefits of this Training&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is actually daily training into focus and prioritization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do this challenge and really commit to it, you’ll find some powerful benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ll start to get good at starting on things.&lt;/strong&gt; This is so important in today’s world of distraction, but it’s always been tough to not run to the habit of procrastination. Getting good at not putting things off is a superhero skill.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ll start to train in staying in the uncertainty of meaningful work.&lt;/strong&gt; If you practice in this invaluable skill, there’s almost nothing you can’t do beyond physical limitations. We stop letting fear and discomfort hold us back. We stop being afraid of difficulty and uncertainty. We cultivate fearlessness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And maybe even launch a project you’ve been waiting your whole life to launch.&lt;/strong&gt; Your love song to the world. If you have a gift to give to the world, it’s a shame to not give it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;join-the-challenge-in-sea-change&quot;&gt;Join the Challenge in Sea Change&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you &lt;a href=&quot;https://seachange.zenhabits.net/&quot; title=&quot;join Sea Change today&quot;&gt;join Sea Change today&lt;/a&gt; (with a 7-day free trial), you can join the challenge and get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An article each week to help you dive into the challenge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A community of people supporting each other, including small teams you can join to hold you accountable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A live video webinar with me, where I give a talk and then answer your questions live&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A huge content of library to help you change the habits you’ve always wanted to change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://seachange.zenhabits.net/&quot; title=&quot;Join Sea Change today (7 days free, then $15/month).&quot;&gt;Join Sea Change today (7 days free, then $15/month).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Helton</name></author><category term="standups" /><summary type="html">There’s nothing we can do more to further our meaningful work and make the impact that we want to make in the world than to:</summary></entry></feed>